Guide to the Burton I. Weiss collection, 1886-1975.
Weiss, Burton I. collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Burton I. Weiss collection, 1886-1975.
7812
Weiss, Burton I.,
1.5 cubic feet.
Correspondence, manuscripts, memorabilia, photographs, printed materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Books, manuscripts, reprints of articles, ephemera, graphics, and proofs collected by Burton Weiss, many of them on gay themes. Included are proofs of novels by Gore Vidal, James Leo Herlihy, Gavin Lambert, and others; play scripts; and film screenplays. Books and bound manuscripts (including proofs, scripts, and screenplays) are cataloged individually. Reprints of articles mainly focus on the biology of hermaphroditism, transsexualism, and sex hormones in mammals. Loose manuscripts include notes and draft pages for the revised edition of Kay Boyle's novel Gentlemen, I address you privately (first published in 1933, second edition in 1991); manuscripts of Lyle Glazier's Tragic America (1974) and Person, place, or thing; an unbound copy of Une collection particulière: 250 images de l'homosexuel dans les livres français, 1605-1969, compiled by Andrea Iezzi (privately printed, 2007); a summary of Karen Rotkin's dissertation, The socio-historical construction of female sexuality (1975); prose and poetry manuscripts by Richard George-Murray; a draft of the article "Designing pacifist films" by Paul Goodman (circa 1960); and a transcript of a session from "Revolutionary males," a seminar conducted by Burton Weiss and Charles Haynie at Tolstoy College, the State University of New York at Buffalo, in the fall of 1972.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American rare book dealer and collector.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Books, manuscripts, reprints of articles, ephemera, graphics, and proofs collected by Burton Weiss, many of them on gay themes. Included are proofs of novels by Gore Vidal, James Leo Herlihy, Gavin Lambert, and others; play scripts; and film screenplays. Books and bound manuscripts (including proofs, scripts, and screenplays) are cataloged individually. Reprints of articles mainly focus on the biology of hermaphroditism, transsexualism, and sex hormones in mammals. Loose manuscripts include notes and draft pages for the revised edition of Kay Boyle's novel Gentlemen, I address you privately (first published in 1933, second edition in 1991); manuscripts of Lyle Glazier's Tragic America (1974) and Person, place, or thing; an unbound copy of Une collection particulière: 250 images de l'homosexuel dans les livres français, 1605-1969, compiled by Andrea Iezzi (privately printed, 2007); a summary of Karen Rotkin's dissertation, The socio-historical construction of female sexuality (1975); prose and poetry manuscripts by Richard George-Murray; a draft of the article "Designing pacifist films" by Paul Goodman (circa 1960); and a transcript of a session from "Revolutionary males," a seminar conducted by Burton Weiss and Charles Haynie at Tolstoy College, the State University of New York at Buffalo, in the fall of 1972.
Graphics include reproductions of drawings by Paul Cadmus. Also included in the collection are catalogs of gay and lesbian studies publications from Bolerium Books and St. Maur.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Weiss, Burton I.,; Boyle, Kay, 1902-1992.; George-Murray, R. (Richard); Glazier, Lyle.; Glazier, Lyle.; Goodman, Paul, 1911-1972.; Haynie, Charles A. (Charles Atkinson), 1935-2001.; Iezzi, Andrea.; Rotkin, Karen.
Subjects:
Book collectors.; Gay men in literature.; Lesbians in literature.; Intersexuality.; Transsexualism.; Hormones, Sex.
Form and Genre Terms:
Printed ephemera.; Manuscripts for publication.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Two J.R. Brussel letters to Henry Miller, ca. 1940, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- John Knowles items, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Litigation of Matthew Cozens and Joseph Nawkins, 1784? (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Ephemera (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "To Edward Carpenter", 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- LGBT pins (MU-2228) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Magazines, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Gay and Lesbian studies, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Greek love, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- St. Maur lists, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Bolerium lists, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Bolerium lists, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "AB 101, The Time Is Now" [VHS tape], n.d.; V-7212 (Box 2)
- Symonds' books, particularly Sexual Inversion, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Paul Cadmus drawings, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Capra Press, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Oswell Blakeston letters to "Gay Sunshine Press", 1978, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "A Star's Progress", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- "Some recent works on the history of same-sex intimacy and homosexuality," Jonathan Katz, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Comments/reviews of gay books, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "Tragic America" and "Person, Place, or Thing," Lyle Glazier, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Proofs of "The Wonder of Beauty...", 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Susan Griffin letters to Tom Parkinson, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Draft?, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, ca. 1950's (Box 3, Folder 12)
- "The Saddest Shul", ca. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- "Une Collection Particuliere," Iezzi/Biffi, 1605-1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- "The Socio-Historical Construction of Female Sexuality," Karen Rotkin (dissertation summary), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Richard George Murray - manuscript material, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- "Revolutionary Males", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- "Designing Pacifist Films," Paul Goodman, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Boyle (Kay), notes and draft pages for revised edition of "Gentlemen, I Address You Privately", 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Boyle (Kay), notes and draft pages for revised edition of "Gentlemen, I Address You Privately", 1991 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Misc. reprints, 1909-1990 (Box 4)
- Reprints concerning hermaphroditism, pseudohermaphroditism, transsexualism, adrenogenital syndrome, and sex hormones, ca. 1940's-1960's (Box 5)
- Movie posters including "Suddenly Last Summer", "Reflections in a Golden Eye", "The Subterraneans", "Midnight Cowboy"; also an unidentified portrait (Map-case Folder)